And welcome
to the Social Services and Community Select Committee.
So this morning we're hearing evidence on the Social Security Jobseeker Support and
Accommodation Supplement Amendment Bill.
And Debbie, I understand you're appearing on behalf of CCS Disability Action.
Welcome.
Oh, thank you. Yes, that is correct.
Can you hear me okay?
We can. We can see and hear you loud and clear.
The time is yours when you're ready.
Okay, perfect. Thank you. Kia ora koutou katoa.
Ko Debbie Ward toku ingoa.
It is my privilege to be providing this oral submission on
behalf of CCS Disability Action,
and thank you for taking the time to read our written submission and the
opportunity to be here this morning to speak with you.
Excuse me.
While we support the principle that income support
should reach the people who most need it, we do have
significant concerns
about the bill as it stands.
The bill applies a new parental assistance test to
all job seeker supportive subtypes, including job
seeker support, health condition, injury, or disability
recipients. It contains no exemption to young people
who hold a medical certificate confirming they cannot work.
This is the single-most important problem with the bill.
Many disabled people cannot access the supported living payment
because its threshold is set very high.
They are directed to the job seeker health
conditions and injury disability instead.
This bill leaves this group without protection.
Basing an 18 or 19-year-old's eligibility on their parents' or
stepparents' income ignores the higher cost disabled
people and their whanau already carry
and creates safety risks for young people who cannot safely
rely on family.
Raising the accommodation supplement entry threshold for some
homeowners while exempting supported living payment recipients,
but not job seekers health conditions and disability
recipients, creates a two-tier system within the
disability community and threatens disabled people's ability to
stay in their own homes.
The government's own regulatory impact statement raises
concerns about the approach for disabled young people and records
that disability organizations were not consulted during the
policy development.
You will see in our written submission that we have made eight
recommendations for the committee's consideration.
These are, introduce a medical exemption,
reconsider the parental assistance test for the job
seekers health conditions and disability recipients,
adjust the income limit for disability costs,
publish the parental support gap test criteria,
exclude stepparents,
extend the accommodation supplement protection,
and require a disability rights impact assessment, and model the
cumulative impact.
If a parental income test proceeds,
we ask that you set a disability-adjusted income limit
that accounts for the documented additional costs
disabled people and their whanau carry.
Resolve internal contradictions in the bill if it
proceeds.
Require the criteria for the parental support gap test to be
published before the bill passes.
Retain the 30%
entry threshold
for job seekers
health conditions and disability recipients, as the bill
already does for supported living payment recipients,
and require a full disability rights impact assessment
consistent with New Zealand's obligation under the United Nations
Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities, Article
4, Section 3, to consult and involve disabled people.
Just want to thank you again for this opportunity to speak, and I'm happy to answer
any questions if I can.
Thank you, Debbie. We've got a question from Ricardo.
Kia ora, Debbie. Thank you so much for your submission.
I've just got two quick questions.
The first one is,
do you support the bill? And do you think this bill has merits?
The second question would be, what do you think would be the potential harm for
disabled people who may be losing their eligibility to income
support and, alongside that, their financial autonomy?
Kia ora, Ricardo. Thank you for your question.
I think what we support is the principle that income
support should reach people who
need it the most.
We do have the concerns around the impacts
for disabled people, or particularly disabled rangatahi,
when currently the bill doesn't take into consideration the
additional costs
that disability carries that
parents of young people or young people themselves may be
experiencing.
But just more specifically, if a disabled 18-year-old,
for example, cannot get access to income support, what do you think will be the
impact on their material realities or their
life outcomes more broadly?
Oh, sure. Yes. Yeah,
definitely the impact on young people that are not entitled to
any income support, they're going to be living very
isolated in their lives. They're not going to have
those abilities to experience
what their non-disabled peers get to experience
necessarily around having friendships,
looking for the opportunities to find jobs, to even leave
home and become more dependent on those
whanau relationships that maybe their siblings
may not have that same dependency.
A question, Maureen?
Hope that makes sense.
Thanks very much, Phoebe. I've got a couple of quick questions as
well.
In
your submission, you're suggesting that
young people should be tested
before going on the job seeker support based on health
condition, injury, or disability.
Just a point of clarification, if you will, are those
in that category,
do they not qualify for ACC support,
or other supported living payments?
Thank you for your question and sorry, I'm Debbie, I'm just filling in for Phoebe
today.
Oh, sorry. Sorry, Debbie.
That's okay.
I think the issue
with the bill at the moment is for young
disabled people on the job seekers support who are
recipients of the job seekers
support under the disability
health and condition criteria.
They
often
fall into that category because the threshold for the supported living payment is
too high, and they don't come into that threshold.
Not all disabled young people are eligible for
ACC
support,
due to maybe their health or medical condition
is not injury related.
Okay, that's really helpful. Thank you.
The other question I have is around your suggestion about excluding
step-parents. So if there was a step-parent in a
relationship in the same household that is contributing
to the household, do you think their
income should not be
tested in terms of ability to support?
The concern that we have is currently it doesn't
align or it's inconsistent with how step-parents are treated for
child support.
Yeah.
So there's some inconsistencies within this bill with the
relationship with step-parents,
with other bills.
Okay.
So we wanted some... Yeah.
Need to get some clarification on that.
Thanks, Debbie.
All right. Well, Mrs. Smith.
No, carry on.
Thank very much, Debbie.
We have no further questions.
Thank you.
But thank you very much for coming in, making a submission.
Thanks for the written submission as well.
Thank you for the opportunity.
Sure.
Thank you, Dean.
The next submitter, I believe, is Citizens Advice Bureau New Zealand via Zoom.
Good after-- good morning rather. We're still in morning. Good morning. Welcome.
Thank you.
Look, thanks for appearing in front of the committee this morning, and we have your
written submission and look forward to hearing from you
in your oral submission.
Kia ora.
I'm just looking. I'm not sure if you can see my colleague Louise. Is she around?
No.
Anyway, I'll make a start.
Yeah.
Yeah. Louise May.
She's been promoted, so yeah, fire away.
Okay, great. Yeah. Tena koutou katoa.
I'm Gwyneth Kerry-Smith, National Data Analyst at the Citizen Advice Bureau,
Ngā Pou Whakawhanaki o Aotearoa. I'm actually speaking
on behalf of Anika Green as well today, our National
Youth Engagement Advisor. She's wanted to be here, but she is unwell.
And with me is Louise May,
another colleague, National Policy Advisor.
So Citizen Advice Bureau is a nationwide community
organization providing free, independent, and confidential information and
advice and advocacy. In the past year,
CAB interacted with around 300 and...
Sorry, 3,003. A lot.
Sorry.
Thank you, Louise. People across Aotearoa with many, many more
interactions
with information provided on our website.
The issues brought to the CAB provide insights into how people are
being affected by laws, policies, and processes, and the barriers that
these systems create in
people's everyday lives. So our submission today is grounded in the
experience of our clients and the hardship that we are seeing in our
communities around the motu. So the CAB does not support this
bill. Young people coming to the CAB
for support are not avoiding work or choosing to rely on
benefits. They are attempting to navigate a labor market that is
increasingly unstable and unlimited, particularly for entry-level
roles. So we support young people with information about their rights,
opportunities, and job hunting, and this might be when they're finishing
study or when they're actively applying for work, but unable to
secure employment. And often, this is despite sustained
effort to get work. So we also support people who have lost
jobs due to business closures or restructuring, who are suddenly without
income and unable to reenter the workforce.
Others move between short-term or casual work and periods where there is
simply no work available. So you'll see some examples from our clients in the
written submission, like the young person that we assisted recently
who has completed his studies, who's doing everything he can to find work, both
applying for temporary summer jobs and roles in his chosen field.
But after months without success, he's approached us to understand how
he can access job seeker support while continuing his job search.
So the examples provided are not unusual cases.
They're representative of the young clients coming to our service who
are on income support or who are needing this support.
And underlying these experiences is a constant pattern that young people are
trying to move forward, but the combination of limited job ability,
housing prices, food prices, and transport barriers
means that their effort does not always translate into stability.
And in this context, the job seeker support functions as a
temporary stability while young people are seeking work, and the
support which is needed more is- Than ever in these tough
economic conditions, and it's disproportionately
impacting young people, those tough economic conditions.
So that context is critical when considering the changes that are
proposed in this bill.
And we're concerned about the bill's introduction of parental income testing
for 18 to 19-year-olds. The assumption underpinning this
change is that young people can reasonably rely on their parents for
support until age 20, and that 18 to
19-year-olds receiving JobSeeker support are doing so out of choice
rather than necessity.
Our experience from assisting young people tells us that these assumptions are
incorrect, and we're concerned that legislation is being made on
the basis of those inaccurate assumptions.
And so, yeah, that's not the reality of the lives that we see,
and that legislation is going to negatively impact these people.
The CAB supports young people who have had to leave home due to violence, abuse,
neglect, or have become estranged from their
family because of serious conflict,
potentially relating to identity, culture, religion, or sexuality.
And we support young people coming out of institutional living and
rangatahi who are living independently with no
ongoing family support.
So many of these young people cannot access parental support because it is not safe
or it simply doesn't exist. So we're concerned that this
policy assumes a level of family support that is just not available for the
young people that we're assisting.
We also have concerns about how this policy would operate in practice.
The CAB observes that people already struggle to navigate MSD
processes, even without this additional complexity overlaying an
entitlement. Introducing a requirement to provide evidence
of family circumstances increases risk of delays,
inconsistent decision-making, and people missing out on support
because they cannot safely or practically provide the documentation
of deeply personal experiences.
So the key risk is not only eligibility criteria, but access and
practice, particularly for those already in crisis.
Also, we would like to point your attention to our recent CAB
Spotlight report, Mana Aki: Dignity for All.
So that's a report that reveals the failures of welfare support here in Aotearoa
New Zealand and explores the steps needed to ensure that people can live with
dignity and in thriving communities.
And this report shows the realities of the hardship that families are already
experiencing. And this amendment is going to further put strain on
families that are already stretched by low incomes,
high housing, and high living costs.
So while this legislation is being framed as a targeted
eligibility change, we believe its impacts will be
much broader in practice, putting up barriers that will mean people in
genuine need of support will not be able to access it
or will face harmful delays in receiving the support they
need. A concern is that the bill would add complexity to
an already difficult system by introducing a new
assessment step, determining whether a young person can reasonably rely on
parental support. In practice, this will require
case-by-case judgment, additional information gathering,
and increased discretionary decision-making.
This will increase the risk of delays, inconsistency, people
falling through the gaps, not because they're ineligible or don't need the
support, but because their circumstances don't fit neatly
into evidential frameworks.
And for young people already in crisis, the situation could be
the difference between stability and immediate hardship,
bearing in mind that many of the young people are also already managing
significant additional stressors, such as housing insecurity,
disability, or health challenges.
Housing is one of the most common issues presented to CAB, and it's
often the pressure point that we see driving people into crisis,
and we believe that reducing young people's access to income support will have
serious knock-on effects for their housing stability and their
safety. The accommodation supplement plays an important role in the
system, but in practice, it doesn't consistently bridge the gap between
incomes and rental costs, and we see people making difficult
trade-offs to maintain their housing stability.
If young people are not able to access the income support they need, those
housing pressures are going to further intensify and quickly,
and it's going to result in more overcrowding, increased demand for emergency
housing, and for some, homelessness.
So we are concerned that this bill will drive the most vulnerable
into further hardship. Our data consistently shows
that hardship is not evenly distributed.
Maori and Pacific peoples are over-represented in our income support
inquiries and in our housing-related hardship inquiries.
We're seeing high levels of need among disabled young people,
LGBTQI+ young people who have experienced family
rejection, care-experienced young people, and young people
experiencing homelessness. And these are also groups where
parental support is more likely to be disrupted or
unavailable. And so while the policy applies
universally to 18 and 19-year-olds, its
impacts will not be evenly experienced.
It's going to disproportionately affect young people already
facing multiple layers of disadvantage.
We would like to say that regarding the fiscal framing of this proposal,
we can see that the bill will not reduce expenditure overall.
It's simply going to redistribute it.
If young people are unable to access income
support when they need it, the costs are going to shift to other parts of the
system. It's going to shift to emergency housing, food support,
debt Mental health services and community
organizations, and I don't think I need to tell
you that these systems are already overstretched.
So our recommendations are that the committee reject
this bill.
If this bill is to be passed,
we would like to see that parental income testing provisions are removed
for 18 and 19-year-olds.
If any form of independence assessment is retained,
that
it is accessible, it's trauma-informed, and it
doesn't place undue burden of proof on young people.
We would like to see MSD processes properly
recognize the circumstances where parental support is
not available,
and that young people's lived experience is central to
any further policy development in this area.
So, in conclusion,
this bill, we believe, will make it harder for young
people to access the support they need to stay
fed, stay housed, stay safe, and
able to build a thriving, independent
future for themselves.
All right. Thank you.
So-
We are well over time, so I won't be able to go to questions, but thanks for making
your submission this afternoon.
Thank you.
Thank you. Morning, rather.
Kia kite.
Thank you. All right, our next submitter is New Zealand Council of
Christian Social Services, live in person.
Community Law first. So sorry? Community Law first.
Sorry. It's Community Law.
Oh, sorry, Community Law. Sorry, my mistake. Sorry.
Community Law Centers Aotearoa also by Zoom, and Rupert, I see you
there, ready to go.
Hello.
Thank you and welcome. We have 10 minutes with you this morning.
Kia ora. Thank you, Joseph.
Good morning.
Tena koutou katoa. Thank you for the opportunity to appear before the committee
today. My name is Rupert O'Brien. I am speaking on behalf of
Community Law Centers Aotearoa, which is the peak body for all 24 Community Law
Centers across the Motu.
And our submission, our written submission in particular, has had significant input
from our member law center, which is Youthlaw,
which is a specialist law center that covers the current entire country and
specializes in giving advice and assistance to young people, and the
people affected most by this bill.
Just to keep line up, that we do not support this bill, and we ask that the
committee recommend that it does not proceed.
Primarily,
this submission will be in relation to the eligibility changes for 18 and
19-year-olds and rangatahi.
First, with regard to the changes to the age of eligibility, we submit that
this really conflicts with other laws and our core understandings in New Zealand,
which has, where people are over 18, they're considered to be full adults.
And they have the same rights and responsibilities as any other citizen,
and they should have the same access to support through MSD as anyone
else. There's not really any reason why someone at age of 18 should be treated
differently from someone age 20.
I also just quickly wanted to talk about the reasoning
behind the benefit cut, which is introduced on the basis that the
idea is,
if the idea is that evidence seems to show that receiving a benefit at a
young age is correlated with long-term benefit receipt or
receiving benefit when they're a bit older.
But we caution the committee to really consider the lack of evidence on this
carefully. Correlation is not causation.
It's not clear that receiving a benefit at a young age actually causes later
benefit receipt. They might just be related.
And it is just as likely, for example, that a young person who struggles to get
employment out of high school may face barriers then throughout their life for the
same reasons that they struggled to get employment directly out of high school.
Young people need support, and they often already face barriers to
self-sufficiency. A weak labor market, if they've got limited work
experience, mental health pressures, unstable housing or unsafe family
circumstances. Removing income support does not remove or
address these barriers. Instead, it just causes hardships.
This also going to cause risks. And we agree with the submission made
by our colleagues at the CAB just before me, that
the process of applying for MSD assistance is already quite difficult.
And where there are barriers in place,
there will be people who are eligible who will not receive their
benefit that they deserve. Youthlaw raised a particular concern about serious
risk of harm and hardship for rangatahi that will result from this cut.
The parental assistance test will be a difficult barrier for young people who are
in unsafe homes or simply cannot rely on their parents for any other
reason. And our experience is that young people are
among the least likely to seek assistance, and they often struggle to
navigate red tape and bureaucracy.
This is just another barrier in front of them to get help that they need.
We ask the committee to look carefully at the real-world behavior that this bill
assumes. And it assumes that rangatahi will be able to understand the
eligibility test, be able to provide the evidence, arrange
appointments to disclose painful or frightening family circumstances to
professionals, and persist through the process when they have little or no money
and no support. In practice, people will not do that, and they will
just either stay in unsafe homes,
and they will not get the support or in the alternative, people who really can't
help,
have to stay safe and have to leave their home will become homeless.
They may face a period of time homeless before they can get assistance or may still
not get assistance. That's just the reality of putting these barriers in places
that some people will not get the assistance that they deserve.
We're also concerned about impact on families.
Proposed parental income threshold is too low in our opinion, in the current
economic climate. Many households are already under significant financial
pressure from rent, mortgage rates, insurance, food,
power, and fuel in particular. The bill effectively asks families
to keep financially supporting young adults while the supports available
when those people were children, such as Working for Families and things like this,
may no longer apply.
We also want the committee to consider the broader economic question.
The reality is that young people do want to work, and they do want to study, and we
saw that immediately post-COVID when there was very low unemployment
stats. When there are options out there, people want to work, but many are right
now entering a difficult labor market, where the people with the least
experience are those least competitive in the labor market, and so the most
affected are those immediately coming out of high school, finishing school with no
experience. Many will rely on casual or short-term work while trying to build
experience or to save for study.
And if Aotearoa removes support while offering limited opportunities, we
should not be surprised to see more young people leave for Australia or elsewhere
for opportunities.
The bill also risks undermining its own stated objectives.
If young people lose eligibility for job seeker support, they're also
losing their connection to MSD and their eligibility for
other supports that MSD provides.
So MSD will provide to a job seeker things such as work brokers and things
like supports for work clothing or other things to help
people get into employment. And it's a perverse incentive, a
perverse outcome to say we want people to be going into employment, but we're
actually going to take away one of the main ways that
your local MSD office can actually assist you to get into that employment.
And so if this bill proceeds, we really strongly recommend an amendment to
preserve people's access to MSD's non-income related work
supports so that MSD can still support rangatahi into employment.
I'll just briefly talk about the accommodation supplement change.
We also oppose this threshold for homeowners, moving from 30% to 40%
of income housing. We note that housing that consumes 30% or more
of household income is already widely treated by people such as the
OECD as unaffordable, and we consider this to be a troubling
shift in what policymakers consider as an acceptable level of housing
stress. It feels like giving up that housing can be affordable,
or that 30% of your income spent on housing is too much, and telling
us that 40% is the level at which it's too much.
But 30% is unaffordable and causes a great deal of stress, and
as our colleagues at the CAB have said, and we echo this,
a lot of people come through our services, and cost of housing is their
kind of key driver of other issues in their life.
And it leads to legal problems that cause them to come into Community Law, to CAB,
and to other support services.
So it's a real base for people, and housing costs
cause a great deal of stress and trouble across people's lives.
In conclusion,
this bill is likely to increase hardship, reduce young people's ability to leave
unsafe circumstances, place additional pressure on whanau and
community services, and to make housing support less responsive to people's real
need. We ask the committee does not proceed with the bill, but if it does, we ask
that at least there are strong connections put in place for people in unsafe family
situations. For example, that when MSD get an
application from a young person who might need to pass
the parental
assistance gap test, that they get their assistance first
and then the test is provided.
Because the gap where you need to go back and get more information,
you need to go talk to a doctor or something, is a gap that is going to make
someone homeless, that's going to cause a great deal of stress and hardship.
So if they could get that assistance first and then go back a couple of weeks later
and provide their proof, and if they don't meet the threshold, fair
enough, they don't get it anymore.
But to provide that stopgap cover,
preserve access to employment supports that MSD provides.
Again, that just makes sense that people can get those
access,
and to avoid changes that normalize severe housing stress as well.
I think I've got a little bit of time for questions.
Thanks, Rupert. Question, Ricardo.
Thank you, Rupert.
Two quick questions. Have you had much experience with the unsupported child
benefit sort of family breakdown test, and what feedback do
you have around the reality and practice of being able to sort
of document that? And secondly, what do you think is the risk for young
people who may be caught in family situations
where they're estranged or there may be violence, and they may not be able to
access that
income support, while they're trying to pass a test
to prove that they have a severe family breakdown?
Yeah. So the reality is that it is not easy
to meet those bars.
It takes time. It takes support from institutions.
And some people will be able to get there, but there may be delays.
There may be that they have to come through Community Law or CAB, who get someone
to advocate for them.
And so you can see delays of weeks to months while people try and meet the
barriers just to access, try and provide the things that they need to provide, and
even then you still see some declines in situations where we'd consider that there
shouldn't be, and those may later be reversed by legal action.
But you can't go back in time and give people the support when they really need
it. And so all these-
Sorry, Ricardo, I just have a quick supplementary from Karen.
Kia ora.
Yeah. My understanding around the
unsupported child's benefit is the frustration
is that you have to have the parent sign off
that there's no further relationship.
So sometimes even with all that support in place, unless a parent's willing to
sign that piece of paper,
that is very, very difficult to move forward.
I hear this often from caregivers.
So that's something that we've made.
But I just wanted to confirm whether that's part of the issue as well, not
necessarily the support of wrapping around them, but actually the
parents signing the form.
Yeah, that is definitely a major problem with the UCB,
although there are ways around it,
MSD can work around that where necessary.
But I think that the
correlation with this is that it's
quite a hard bar to hurdle,
and there are always delays in association with that.
And the thing that we see, is that if you're
wanting to get
absolute proof, the sort of proof that MSD accept for these kinds of things,
and we understand that they will be looking for things like doctor's notes,
and not accepting things like community support as evidence,
that it's hard to get to doctors. It's hard to get to
your support people and get the evidence that you need.
And I think that we need to take youth's experience with
this, is that young people don't seek support.
They don't actually want to go through and they don't want to talk to
people, and they don't want to explain their family
circumstances to someone they don't know. And they will not do it.
So they might be as willing to go as far as to seek income support,
but a lot of people will struggle or will straight up just not
seek the necessary support to meet that parental assistance
test.
Thanks Rupert for coming and making a submission this morning, and thanks for the
written submission as well.
Kia ora.
The next submitter is New Zealand Council of Christian Social Services,
and it looks like we're online and in person. Okay.
Hi, Rupert.
Excellent. Great. Welcome.
Good afternoon, and the time is yours Marie.
Thank you. Kia ora koutou. Thank you very much for having me today.
So I'm Alicia Sutton. I'm the Kaiwhakahaere Matua of the New Zealand Council of
Christian Social Services, and joined also by Mel online, who will speak shortly as
well. So we are an umbrella organization for Christian Social Services across
the Motu. Our services provide a range of support for New Zealanders
from budgeting, food bank, youth services,
housing, all of that. So everything that we do as an organization is
informed by their insights and experiences as providers and with
the people that they support. So our submission today is going to be focused on the
changes to 18 and 19-year-old job seekers.
And I want to start with providing a bit of context for the situation that our
young people are growing up in. So today, our organization released our
report, Kua Mahue, Left Behind, which brings to light the
persistent and pervasive nature of poverty in Aotearoa, bringing together
government data and insights from our frontline social
services. The report reiterates the high rate of child poverty we have
in New Zealand and the ongoing cost of living and income challenges facing a lot of
parents. For children raised in poverty, we know the odds are stacked against
them. Growing up in hardship impacts their educational attainment, ongoing
employment and income into adulthood.
This year, there are still
169,300 children living in material
hardship who are not having their basic needs met.
That's almost 50,000 more children than we had in 2022.
MSD's 2024 child poverty report shows that there's a higher
number of children from working households than in benefit households who are in
hardship as well. We know that parents are already doing it really
tough. One of the client voices from our report that was shared with us by
Vision West said, and I quote, "Working class families like mine
can't afford what we need to survive." End of quote.
We therefore oppose this bill due to concerns that it will increase hardship among
young people and their families, and we recommend instead that investment goes into
supporting the aspirations of our young people.
I'll pass over now to our senior policy analyst, Mel, who's online, who will share
more specifics about our concerns with the bill.
Thanks, Alicia. So our primary concern with this bill is
regarding its potential to increase financial hardship and create further
barriers to employment or training for young people.
Research indicates that more working households are experiencing financial hardship
and demand for food has increased, and at the same time, our young people are
going into a challenging job market.
The number of young people not in employment or training is at a 10-year high.
This change would mean that some young people face further barriers to accessing
support to enter employment or training, such as that provided by
MSD when receiving a benefit.
We recommend instead that there's increased investment in services that address
known barriers to employment, such as addressing numeracy and literacy
barriers, enabling access to driver's licenses, strengthening
employment supports available to young people, and increasing investment in
culturally appropriate employment and training services.
We're also concerned that the income test does not adequately recognize the
differing costs, financial hardship, or barriers to employment that some young
people and their families may face.
An example of this is hardship among disabled young people and their families, and
we're concerned that this change weakens the safety net that we have under the
Social Security Act for those for whom work is currently not
appropriate due to sickness, injury, disability, or caring
responsibilities. And again, if unable to access job seeker
support, these young people may also lack support to enter employment or
training. We're concerned that families will be worse
off financially or disincentivized from taking on more work due to the
impact that earning above this threshold may have on the young person's
ability to access job seeker support.
And we recommend that if we're treating young people as dependents in one part of
the system, that we also reflect this in other parts of our
system, such as ensuring that Working for Families continues to be
available to families of young people affected by this change.
We support the inclusion of young people who have been in care and
those who have had a caregiver receiving the unsupported child's benefit within the
criteria of those meeting this parental support gap
test.
But we're concerned that this test will further isolate young people who
cannot rely on their family for financial support, but who are unable to
satisfy MSD's criteria.
We're concerned that the test will not reflect the complexity of financial and
relational stresses that may exist for a young person and their
family. So, in summary, we do not support this bill, and we
recommend that it does not progress.
Thank you. Who's questioning? Dana.
Thank you.
I note your points relating to young people and the
ability to get
support from MSD.
Could you give me your view on what would happen if they
received a student allowance and did training of some description
instead?
Yeah, I think in general, I guess the critical concern is both the access to
income coupled with the lack of training supports that they will get as a
result of not being able to access JobSeeker.
So, if there was a opportunity for them to still get
income while unemployed,
we'd be open to that. But I think given student allowance is only for those who are
training,
I'm not sure how we would expand the criteria for that one.
So, isn't... Oh, sorry. Isn't the idea that
they may not be able to get JobSeeker support, but they could get a
student allowance if they did some training, which would improve their opportunity
to get a job or get further ahead? I'm just asking the
question because that seems to be the logic, but perhaps you have a different
view.
Yeah, absolutely. And for those who are capable, have the capacity and the cost and
access to education, student allowance absolutely is a really great option for
helping support students through their studies.
But we know that's not possible for everyone, and we know that we currently have
such a high rate of young people not in employment and education.
And so there are often, for many of those young people, steps that might need to be
taken to support them before they might be ready for tertiary training or other
training where you can access student allowance and those existing support
systems.
I want to ask a supplementary on this because it's been on my mind as well.
So, the focus of submission so far has been on the challenging job market and-
Mm-hmm
... and unemployment or employment.
Whereas, this is focused on employment, education or training.
And isn't it a good outcome to focus young people's minds,
and their family's minds if they support them, to get into education and training
if they're coming out of school so they actually can up-skill themselves and
prepare themselves for a job market and new job opportunities?
Yeah, absolutely. And that's why I think we're concerned about the fact that if
they aren't able to get a benefit, it means they can't also get those supports that
MSD provides while someone is on a benefit to help them be more work ready or
training ready or connect them to those appropriate programs that otherwise young
people might not know about. And I think as Mel mentioned, we also note that
there's a cohort who would have got the JobSeeker Health Condition Disability
benefit, which based on the criteria means that someone isn't able to work
temporarily.
So, the loss of that would be really concerning because that shows that a young
person isn't actually, doesn't have the capacity to work at that time.
But the
student allowance is available for
young people who are studying.
Yeah, absolutely. And it's great for people who are studying, but not everyone
might be ready, able to access it, or that it's not the right pathway for
everyone.
Well, again-
So, their pathway is to stay on the JobSeeker benefit.
I understand that people, not everybody can work.
Mm-hmm.
I get that.
Yeah.
And there are some people who won't be able to, and I fully accept that.
But what do they do if they don't want to go and do training?
Yeah, and that's why I think MSD's got a really great range of supports to provide
for young people, and we just encourage more investment into that.
It can be making sure that they know how to interact with the job.
If for some young people, it might be their first job, and how to make sure you've
got the right clothes, you've got the right gear.
All of that kind of support that not everyone might already know, and can be really
challenging. So that pastoral care element is really critical.
We've seen success with programs like Mana and Mahi, where it's both got connection
to employment as well as pastoral care, and it really gets them ready for the job
market. So, we really support the programs that are available and want to make
sure that connection continues, and one of the key connection points is the
MSD system.
Okay.
I'm keen for you to talk more to the challenge in
terms of there not being enough jobs for our young
people. I gave an example recently where over 1,200 people applied
for one cleaning job in Auckland. And that might also tie
into if you're not eligible for JobSeeker benefit, what other support
is there to help broker you-
Mm-hmm
... into jobs?
Yeah, absolutely. And we definitely hear that from our frontline services, that
people are just putting in applications and they're not even getting responses
back. The challenge that that has when you're, especially when you're a young
person trying to enter the job market, and how that makes you feel just getting
rejection after rejection at that time.
So it's really challenging for young people, and not everyone knows how to navigate
that. How to write a cover letter to get that support is really critical so that
they can actually be ready for jobs, and find them.
So,
we think that it's important that those training services are there to
help build capability. But it is really difficult at the moment.
Even if people who are job ready aren't able to find jobs.
I mean-
It's
Yeah. We hear similar stories to what you shared about there being thousands of
applications-
Mm
... for some jobs, particularly in regional areas at the moment. Yeah.
Well thanks, Elysia and Melanie for appearing and making submissions this
afternoon.
Awesome. Thank you very much.
Thank you.
All right, our next submitter is the New Zealand Council of Trade
Unions.
Hearing online? Looks like online.
All right. Good afternoon and welcome.
We've got 10 minutes with you this afternoon. The time is yours when you're ready.
Kia ora. Kia ora tātou. My name is Rachel Mackintosh.
I'm the Vice President of the New Zealand Council of Trade Unions, Te Kāwai
Kainahi. We represent the interests of our 32 affiliated trade
unions and more than 370,000 union members across
the country. We appreciate the opportunity to submit today.
The CTU is strongly opposed to this bill.
Means testing 18 and 19-year-olds for welfare support based on
their parents' income will increase poverty and hardship among young people and
their whānau. There aren't enough jobs being created in New Zealand right
now, and so- No matter how hard people try to find a job, they're not always
going to be successful. And we know that young people are particularly
hard hit during economic downturns, as they tend to have fewer
employable skills, less work experience, and are more likely to
work in precarious situations. So simply
eliminating job seeker support for a large subset of 18 and
19-year-olds won't do anything to improve this
situation. I will now hand over to Jack Foster, who will speak to
our submission in more detail, focusing on the changes to job seeker
support eligibility. Jack.
Thank you, Rachel.
Hello there. My name's Jack. So yeah, I'll speak briefly to four issues.
So the labor market context, the likely negative effects of the
bill, the complexity the bill introduces, and what
a better approach could look like.
So to the first issue,
as you know, the labor market has weakened significantly over the past three years
due to a combination of higher interest rates, international shocks,
and government policy,
and unemployment is now at 5.3%, which is around its highest
level in a decade. That means over 160,000 people
out of work in the March 2026 quarter, which is the largest
number of people out of work since the early 1990s.
In this context, youth unemployment has rapidly risen.
So for 15 to 19-year-olds, unemployment has increased from around
14% in 2022 to over 23% in
2026, and the neat rate has risen as well, although not by
as much.
And this has happened not because young people have suddenly become lazy or
workshy, but because of the dire state of the job market.
So in this context, even highly motivated job seekers can find it impossible to
get work because there aren't enough jobs available, or they have been
out-competed by older workers with more experience.
And so although the removal of support that this bill brings in
may incentivize some people to enter educational training, the reality
is that others will not be in a position to do so.
This is because some young people
face major barriers to entering educational training.
This can include a lack of foundational literacy or
numeracy skills,
severe mental health issues, or even practical barriers like not having a
driver's license.
So preventing some young people from access to job seekers will
exacerbate these issues. Access to many of MSD's employment
support services, as you know, is contingent on being a recipient of a main
benefit. And so this means that some young people rendered ineligible for job
seekers will also be shut out of services that could help them get into
employment or into a training course.
Given this, it's not surprising that MSD's advice to government was that although
this policy will save the Crown some money in the short run, it is quite possible
it will result in higher costs in the long run.
So this is because some people who have been denied job seeker support when they
were 18 and 19 will nevertheless need to take up that support
when they turn 20, and will be doing so, in some cases, from a worse
starting position, having potentially spent the last two years in severe
hardship. And this actually puts them at greater risk of long-term benefit
dependency.
Nothing.
In addition, the increased poverty and hardship caused by the carve-out is likely
to result in higher costs to the Crown and housing, health, and the justice system,
and it will certainly result in higher costs for communities in the form of
increased strain on families, greater unmet health need, and declining
social cohesion.
So to the second issue, the bill sets the parental income level for eligibility
very low,
and the reality is that many people earning over this threshold will struggle to
support their adult children, particularly given the ongoing cost
crisis. The situation will be particularly difficult for young people living
with a health condition or disability, as they tend to face higher living costs
than other cohorts. Some young people affected by this bill will
also be refused support by their parents.
Other young people may be compelled to remain in dangerous household environments,
and still others might be incentivized to engage in the informal economy to get
by.
The bill has a theoretical safeguard against some of these risks, in the parental
support gap determination, but it'll be difficult for many
benefit claimants to navigate
this in many cases.
And this leads me to the issue of complexity.
So as the Welfare Expert Advisory Group found in its landmark
2019 report, "Agreement is near
universal that the benefit and tax credit systems are unmanageably
complex." Yet what this bill does is introduce further unnecessary
complexity to the system.
Sections 23A to I of the bill are very
complex and will create an increased administrative burden for MSD.
But more importantly, the added complexity will mean that some young people who are
eligible for job seekers, either because their parents' income is below the
threshold or because they cannot rely on their parents for support, will
make failed applications or will neglect to apply altogether.
So what would a better approach to the problem look like?
So domestic and international evidence shows that the most effective
way to support people off benefits and into work is to provide
education and training opportunities, personalized employment services,
job matching programs, and in some cases, wraparound one-on-one
support.
So these are collectively referred to as active labor market programs.
And in New Zealand, we have an active labor market system, but parts of the system
are fragmented and under-resourced, as research from MSD and also
independent think tanks has demonstrated, and we also spend notably
less on the system than many of our OECD peers.
So when it comes to the supply side issues, lifting our game on ALMPs is
probably the best place to start. And beyond that, and this gets
perhaps beyond the scope of the submission, but we need to be looking at our macro
industrial and education policies and how they can be reoriented
towards delivering full employment so that everyone who wants to work
can work. So I'll leave my remarks there. Thank you.
Oh, thank you. I might just make a comment and then a question.
The
challenging job market is not the case within all of New Zealand.
I know my region, the Southland,
in fact, what I'm hearing from
business leaders is that the biggest concern is not enough people.
But just a comment. But in terms of a question, and you
touched on it, Jack, just at the end of your submission there around education and
training, because obviously the focus of this is
getting young people into employment, education or training.
So I'd just ask if
you
clearly... Well, would you agree that educational
training is probably the most effective way that young people can up-skill
themselves for the future job market?
Yeah, absolutely. And so the idea
behind improving our ALMP system is to ensure that people who are
hard to access or who aren't uptaking education and training
can get the support they need. And as you've heard, as we mentioned, and as you
heard from
other submitters, one of the kind of unfortunate impacts of this bill
is that by preventing some young people from
accessing a main benefit, they'll also be prevented from accessing
key supports from MSD that would actually help them get that
education and training that they need.
So, I
guess intent behind this bill is not going to be
delivered on. Yeah. And fair enough on the comment on
Southland, but I would mention that the majority of the country is seeing a very
weak labor market. There's some pockets of strength in the South Island, which is
great, but the vast majority of the country is in quite bad shape.
Thanks. Helen?
I wanted to ask about the active labor market policies in other
countries. How many of them are hand in hand
with not having any kind of financial support for that person,
or making them have to borrow the money for
training as the alternative? I've been
impressed by one that I saw in Copenhagen,
but please feel free to comment on any that you know in terms of
the basis for active labor market solutions.
Yes, I can't give you a number on how many would be without providing
financial support. But what we see internationally as the most
effective systems are ones where all the
different parts of the system are linking up.
So you've got
job seekers are put in touch with the right sets of support,
and sometimes that involves not just getting them
in front of education and training opportunities, but also getting
things like mentoring, practical assistance with really basic
things like getting a driver's license or learning how to do time
management, or getting people the kind of mental health support
services they need. And so sometimes-
Sorry, this is last question. Dana, we're just running short on time.
Thanks.
Firstly, I echo Joseph's comments.
In my region, the employers will tell you they can't find people to come and do the
jobs,
no matter how hard they try. So, they are field-
What region is that, sorry?
Tairāwhiti. They are field jobs, lots of them.
But anyway, my question, sorry, I'm out of time now,
is
what do you say then to the parents who email me,
telling me they're at their wits end because they cannot get their 18 and
19 year olds to go and do some training or apply for jobs,
because it's easy for them to be on the job seeker benefit?
Yeah, I would need to see those emails, I guess, to
see
the kind of scale at which this is
a real problem. But what I would say is that
it's not an easy thing to fix, but
simply taking away
support will only increase the problem.
So if you've got an unmotivated job seeker, taking
away their support is not actually going to get
to the root of the problem.
All right. Well, thank you Jack and Rachel for making submission.
Thanks for the written submission as well.
Thanks.
All right. Next submitter is St Peter's on Willis Social Justice
Group in person.
Keeping it professional.
Well, good afternoon. We have 10 minutes with you this afternoon.
The time is yours when you're ready.
Thank you, Joseph Mooney, for welcoming us and for the
opportunity to speak to the Social Services and
Community Committee on the Social Security Job
Seeker Support and Accommodation Supplement Amendment Bill.
My name is Gail Duncan, and I'm accompanied by Steven Jenkins,
and I chair the St Peter's on Willis Social Justice Group of St Peter's
Anglican Church, Te Aro. And we have other supporters here from St
Peter's Anglican Church, which is Judy sitting at the back there.
The purpose of our submission is to highlight the course of
action proposed by the two initiatives in the bill that they
impinge on human rights.
The first places unnecessary surveillance on both the
young persons and their associated families.
This involves costly use of department time and takes the
focus away from ensuring young people have the
independence and income security in their own hands, their
responsibility, that they deserve to progress to become
productive adults.
The rationale for the second initiative of raising the entry
threshold criteria for homeowners, those paying a mortgage,
on the grounds that the government shouldn't cover the cost of private ownership-
is in conflict with the government's supporting landlords
directly with accommodation supplements. We feel that's very two-faced.
The two proposed initiatives in total go against the
definition of social spending to protect households from shocks
that adversely affect, impact the
incomes and welfare.
These initiatives will be completely counterproductive and add a burden
to young people aged from 16 to up to 20, about to
enter our economy as self-sufficient, productive units,
and upon persons deemed to be family of that young person.
The rapid legislation to enact clampdown in the
budget on social spending clearly highlights a lack of vision in
the budget, and reinstates surveillance measures
rejected by New Zealand society to squeeze out
the last cent from those already in tightened circumstances
due to high unemployment resulting from constrained government spending.
The rationale used by government ministers in the first reading of this
bill that the welfare system must support those with no other
resources and mustn't be applied to those accumulating
real assets, and that hardworking New Zealanders shouldn't have their
taxes going to support welfare payments, is a construct of
right-wing thinking. Welfare dependency,
that term is constructed
to position New Zealanders who use the welfare system as
unworthy weights upon the righteous workers, without thinking
of the consequences to society as a whole of not
providing income support to those in most need.
The Social Justice Group want to see the bill paused, the two
initiatives removed, and the strategy of tightening
criteria on those with the least to balance the
books shelved, and new ways to gain revenue and to
support persons in those situations considered.
Sustainable Development Goals, United Nations, and other
international agreements the government has pledged to, including the Treaty of
Waitangi, are all underpinned by the right to support
persons in such circumstances. And the government, we think, is
committed to exercise its responsibilities.
What is the purpose of rapid legislation to enact a
clampdown in the budget on social spending, when the latest
books show that less spending than allocated was conducted in the first
10 months ending 30 April?
Over 160,000 New Zealanders are out of work, with nearly
65,000 unemployed for nearly six months.
By stripping young people in these circumstances of support
when they can't fend for themselves, where will they go?
When they find themselves out on the street, because many are not directly
associated with families, will you sweep them up in the next
legislation proposal of move-on orders?
Mm.
Will emergency accommodation be a prison cell with future
prospects for those young people nullified?
Any person in New Zealand can find themselves at any moment in a
situation of unemployment. We in Wellington, in the public service know that
quite well. People who have been employed for 40
years and are still paying a mortgage would not manage once they are
unemployed. Are you intending to maximize the chance
that they will lose their one major asset via arrears and
foreclosure, and move them over to rental, or worse, by your
second initiative?
Those impacted are mostly non-beneficiaries.
They are low to middle-income working households.
68.8% are families with children.
That's the majority, with children.
Considering the potential impact on these children who could be
driven into poverty must be paramount.
The bill is a product of a budget in which the burden of fiscal
restraint is falling disproportionately on low-income
families, disabled people, Maori communities,
public sector workers, and others facing disadvantage.
The St Peter's on Willis Social Justice Group requests the first
initiative is completely withdrawn, as it includes a type of
mass surveillance to ascertain the relationship status of the young person,
and deprives the young person of the right to be considered
separately from his or her families.
And for the second initiative, the
Social Justice Group recommends that the government takes the advice of
MSD to consider the impacts of the proposal
in light of the cost of living pressures on homeowners, impact
on Maori and Pacific peoples, including the lower home
ownership rates amongst these peoples, and reflect on the
fact that this provision was originally meant to reduce
housing-related stress on all low-income households.
And that a proportion of a person's income spent on
accommodation these days has grown, which explains the
growth in cost to government.
Some homeowners may decide or be forced to manage this
by selling their home, which will lead to long-term housing
insecurity, which would defeat the purpose.
The impacts of housing insecurity include poorer health, poorer
education outcomes for children, and finding it harder to get a job.
As Maori are heavily impacted by this bill, the Crown has an
obligation under Article 1 of the Treaty of Waitangi to act in
good faith, including consulting with Maori.
MSD has also reported that the savings forecast may be
overestimated.
MSD recognizes that there will be a potential impact of
homelessness being the only option remaining for some,
including families with children
Other forms of hardship assistance have not been
modeled as part of the forecast savings.
This means the cost of the proposal on other forms of hardship
assistance may be underestimated.
To conclude, we request the Select Committee
considers the rapid introduction of this bill with
no proper consultation with affected parties, including the young
persons, and no consideration of impact on the well-being
or future prospects for them goes against the principles
of social security and social license, which
allows government to operate. It will bring unnecessary
hardship. We already see it with the constraints at the moment.
It's evident before you in plain sight, and will not deliver
any effective benefits to our economy.
The bill should be paused until after the budget has been fully
accepted by Parliament, and for a further period of time
to allow an appropriate period of consultation with the
public, including the time required to meet the terms of
Treaty of Waitangi obligations. Thank you very much for your time.
All right. Question, Helen?
I want to ask about your comment about the
unworthy weight, I think you called it.
Yes.
I've been thinking about the difference of parenting, and it really applies
to both paths of what you're talking about today.
Mm.
We need more children in this country.
Teenagers are really difficult.
We value what parents do with teenagers at this age because it
keeps them alive, and it makes them productive later, and it's going to help us.
What do you think about that value that
those particular kids and those parents of those kids
have in terms of these proposals?
Well, it isn't valuing that dynamic which you just mentioned.
And our proposal of allowing the child as they move out,
or
the young adult, as they move out into society to have an
independent income.
And then you can shape around that, those other
forms of assistance which would include life skills
for the young people. There have examples back
many moons ago of the Salvation Army, for example, picking
up young unemployed after they leave school and
doing, say they did conservation work, they were paid the
benefit and
in addition to that, there was an expectation of learning life skills, how to
manage your money, get your license, or if you already had your license, how to
drive a car properly. So all those practicalities which took a bit of a burden
off the parents and made the child think forward as a future
prospect for their life and contribution to society.
Thank you.
Well, thanks, Carol. Thank you for making a submission this afternoon.
All right. The next submitter is, I believe
.
Oh, Benjamin Huxford. Okay, excellent.
Benjamin Huxford.
Yeah.
We've
swapped out someone else who wasn't available for me.
Right.
Excellent. All right, thanks, Benjamin.
Welcome. We've got five minutes with you this afternoon.
The time is yours when you're ready.
Hi. Oh, yes. Thank you.
Hi. It's been a bit of a
time for me. I've been doing a few submissions recently.
This is the first one I've done, so I'm going a bit
more off the cuff. I haven't had a lot of time to prepare, otherwise,
I would've liked to. I feel pretty strongly about this bill.
So a lot of what I'm going to be talking about will probably be largely
testimonial.
If you've read the thing in there, you know that I've kind of struggled with
work in the past.
And
getting back into work has been a big part of my journey into my 20s.
One thing I did not mention
which I think is probably relevant for this bill is that while my
early 20s being
difficult,
to say the least, it doesn't quite line up with the 16, 19 light threshold
that's discussed in the bill. One important thing
that I feel like was worth disclosing is that I
spent a lot of my time with my family in and out of dealings
with Oranga Tamariki.
And during that time, particularly when I just left home, I
tried to reconnect with my dad, and it ended horribly.
And during that time, I was very well aware of the supports that I had in place,
and that
were it not for some very key people at some very key times, I would
be kind-- I
don't really know
what to think.
Yeah. Or what I think I would've done
during that time.
Yeah. I noted
when that happened is that at least in my 20s, I felt more capable of
myself. I could not imagine going through similar struggles and
similar issues if
things got more abusive in my family, for instance,
at key times, and I thought that I would have to leave.
Yeah. Which were definitely things I had considered and contemplated
during that time.
Yeah.
Sorry, this is a lot for me.
Mm.
But yeah. I've just been very aware that
it was an even more vulnerable moment for me during that time
of late teenagehood.
And
I'm even aware of the small amount that the accommodation supplement they gave me,
usually oscillating between $60 and $100,
was significant enough to me that a lot of the times it became the difference
between whether I ate or not.
Yeah.
My family didn't have a lot of money.
A lot of the times I would have to loan my parents, my
mom particularly, money from the paper round money that I'd done to make sure that
we had enough food to eat.
My degree of poverty, I think for the
time, wasn't
significant, but what I've noticed more and more is that's becoming more and more
frequent over the last decade. And that
terrifies me, and I feel for the children of today
and what they're going to have to live through.
I'm currently in positions where I'm hoping to pay back a bit for what I can and
use the skills that I have to go into
social services, maybe become a support worker.
So I'm very interested in making sure that this bill...
What am I saying? I think there's a lot of problems with this bill, and
I fear that if a lot of the things come to pass that are currently in this bill,
that there is a strong possibility that we will
spread ourselves too thin and that many more people will fall through the cracks.
As somebody who's looking at doing a career to help people who will be in this
situation, I don't think
that it is--
Yeah.
I think that's a genuine concern that needs to be had still. Yeah, sorry.
No worries. You should carry on.
I think you made a really interesting point about you going through it in your
20s. These people will be going through it so young.
How will they navigate that, and wouldn't it just
overwhelm your average
kid of that age?
So I wanted
to put a suggestion to you, which was in one of the other submissions, was one
thing that was really important for them, was that there was
support in the interim while things were sorted out.
Can you talk about that and whether you see a value in that submission?
I think
there definitely is. I think there needs to be a lot more focus
on making sure that tamariki, young people, are
supported during those times.
I
mean, I'm
struggling now. But
yeah.
There definitely needs to be more
resources put towards that.
Yeah, okay. Yeah.
Thank you.
No, thank you, Adrian. Thank you very much. Social Development.
All right. And the next submitter is Salvation Army, Te Ope Whakaora.
We've already got this one. Te Hunga Roa?
No, they're not.
They don't have them.
Salvation Army.
We're good.
Okay, cool.
Good afternoon,
Paul.
Yeah. Good afternoon. There we go. We can see and hear you. Welcome.
We've got 10 minutes with you this afternoon. Time is yours. And Nolan.
Hi.
Welcome. And yes, I've got Nolan Hill
joining us as well. So, tena koutou katoa, and thank you for the opportunity to
speak to you today.
My name's Paul Barber. I'm a senior social policy analyst with the Social Policy
and Parliamentary Unit, Salvation Army, and I'm joined today by
Nolan Hill, who is the national
children and youth development advisor for The Salvation Army.
Our written submission is before you, and our comments
in our submission cover both aspects of this bill,
the increasing of the threshold for homeowners to access the accommodation
supplement and introducing a parental income test for 18 and 19-year-olds
on the JobSeeker benefit.
Our submission really recommends that these changes not proceed.
The changes to the accommodation supplements we consider to be
counterproductive to the aims of social policy, such as supporting
low income households into home ownership and reducing
material hardship.
And we disagree with the assertion that the policy is based on, that
40% of income
is an acceptable level of housing costs for lower income
households.
We believe that proceeding with this will be increasing hardship
for already financially stressed households.
But today, we'd really like to focus on the parental income test changes around the
JobSeeker benefit, and I'm going to hand over to Nolan,
who is a very experienced children and youth worker, who'll share from his wide
experience working with vulnerable young people about some of the likely aspects
that the changes to the JobSeeker benefit will make. Over to you, Nolan.
Thanks, Paul. Thanks for your time today.
As Paul mentioned, I want to speak to some of the tension points I see around the
proposed legislative changes, as I feel these changes will
cause extra harm to our most vulnerable young people who are trying
to navigate into adulthood.
Any stories that I now share I've anonymized to protect the privacy
of the young people.
My background over the last nine years has been in a local NGO,
where we worked in the youth transitions into independence space
and alternative education,
so I have firsthand knowledge of the impacts
for this demographic.
I speak specifically today to the parental support gap test, especially
where it is proposed to use a similar assessment as that of the current youth
payment test.
And my first point is around the hidden harm within the family/whanau
unit.
One young person did not meet the threshold for the family
breakdown under the youth
For family breakdown under the youth payment criteria, manipulation,
power, and control were all present.
However, the distress and harm was hidden when the assessments were
made. Despite the young person's youth advocates raising concerns,
the assessment framework couldn't factor in the reality for this particular young
person's situation.
It took seven months of fighting on behalf of this young person to gain meaningful
traction, and this even included a local MSD manager, who
themselves struggled to have the system respond appropriately for this young person
to remain on youth payment.
So you can see from this brief example that any assessment process needs to
be flexible enough to respond to the many unique, challenging
situations our young people find themselves in.
My second point is who should be supporting a vulnerable
young 18 or 19-year-old? Yes, there may be situations where this
legislative change may work, where a parent's
relationship with their child is healthy and there is enough income to sustain
support. However, this cannot be assumed to be the norm for this
demographic, sadly.
Another situation was where a young woman
had to leave home due to a breakdown in family
relationship and concerns about her safety.
She was
temporarily living with her boyfriend because she had no viable alternative.
Prior to turning 18, she'd been
assured by her youth service worker that her youth payment would transition
seamlessly into the job seeker support.
In practice, this did not occur, creating significant uncertainty and hardship for
her.
The concern here was that the assessment process appeared to assume that because
she was living with her boyfriend, she could reasonably rely on him for
financial support. This failed to recognize that the relationship itself was not
always stable or healthy, and maintaining some financial independence
was crucial for her well-being and safety.
Rather than being assessed as needing independent financial
support, an expectation seemed to be that she should first rely
on her abusive mother,
then on the boyfriend, and then potentially his parents, before being
considered eligible for assistance in her own right.
This assessment effectively placed her in a position of financial dependence on her
boyfriend, despite the vulnerabilities already present in her circumstances.
Again, in this situation also, the risks of coercion, manipulation or
unhealthy power dynamics within the partner relationship didn't get picked
up in her reassessment for youth payment and moving through into job seekers.
My next point is around the assessment process.
Is it a face-to-face local assessment or a remote phone
call?
Another case highlights the further concern about current assessment models for
youth payment,
that are also being considered now, as I mentioned, for the proposed parental
support get test. The process began for this
individual with an MSD social worker based in Auckland
conducting an assessment over the phone.
For many vulnerable young people, discussing deeply personal or
traumatic experiences with an unfamiliar person over the
telephone is extremely difficult.
As we know, building trust is often essential before a young person feels safe
enough to disclose family harm or abuse, and then
that's even face-to-face, let alone on the phone.
In the next part of the process, a second assessment was later undertaken by a
locally based community contracted
social worker. And here's a quote from a local social worker youth advocate
for the young person.
"The local contracted social work assessors were brilliant and reached out to
everyone needed. The phone calling from the youth payment team, however, was not
adequate, and my young person could not understand the things they said.
They needed support in person to ensure they understood and then have support
provided later after talking about difficult things in their lives."
So this raises questions about whether family breakdown assessments should continue
to be managed through a nationalized system involving phone calls.
I suggest a locally managed approach similar to that used for
unsupported child benefit assessments.
This may allow assessors to engage with the young person's support networks,
understand local context, and get a more complete picture of
their circumstances.
When decision-makers are geographically removed from the young person's
environment, important contextual information can be missed.
My fourth point is the stress caused by delays in decision-making.
Whether a disputes, delays, or uncertainty about eligibility, young people can
experience lengthy gaps before support is
approved. The question then becomes: What happens during this period?
For a young person who is unable to safely return home and has limited
support networks, a delay in assessment can mean having no income at all,
and this increases vulnerability to homelessness, financial hardship,
unhealthy dependence on others,
or exploitation.
Any assessment framework should prioritize minimizing these risks to ensure
vulnerable young people are not left without financial support while
decisions are being made.
And finally, a broader concern is the mixed messages we give our young
adults as to when they are to enter adulthood and
independence.
At 18 years of age, a young person can vote, enter
legal contracts, and are generally regarded as adults in many areas of society.
But when it comes to financial support, they may be still expected to rely on their
parents as their primary source of income. This creates mixed messages.
In closing, these stories example the kinds of distress that will become more
common because of this bill.
So please take the above points into consideration, I ask you.
I urge decision-makers to firstly consult with young people and their trusted adult
advocates when designing the parental support get test.
And secondly, if the assessment process is stalled for the parental support get
test, then before creating a period of financial hardship and vulnerability
for the young person
... that there is a provision made for the availability of an
interim support payment that will see a young person through.
Appreciate your time today. Thanks.
No, thank you. Quick question from me.
Given your experience, would you agree that generally, that
18 to 19-year-old
age range is really important as there's usually a transition
from the family and schooling into
adulthood, and decisions made around that point of time are really important?
So a focus on employment, educational training
is a good objective.
Absolutely.
And we need some key markers to send our young adults into
adulthood. And in an ideal situation, the parent would provide
the building blocks and then the confidence to
push the young people out into these opportunities of
pre-employment training and employment itself.
However, some lack the role modeling and example at home, so we need
workplace mentoring and we need external to the workplace
mentors that young people trust to give them that
graduated exposure where there has been no modeling at home.
No, thank you very much, Paul and Nolan.
Appreciate you coming and making a submission this afternoon.
Thank you.
Cheers.
All right, our next submitter is Adam Land.
In person?
I'll check the corridor again, but we might not-
Okay. While we, should we just...
Anya?
Or Anna, is it?
No.
All right, we don't appear to have those two submitters, so that will conclude our
submissions this afternoon.
We can suspend.